Alright, next up in our instructing and coaching modules is
something called our Count, Cue,
Encourage method. So, what is it?
It's literally what it says. When we're coaching our clients,
we go through counting and cueing and encouraging.
When we're instructing exercise. So,
count, it is literally counting,
being concise and being accurate with the word,
with the numbers that you're counting during the sessions.
Why? Obviously, it ensures that the clients are performing the correct number of repetitions.
It helps them know where they're up to,
which is very important, and it helps you know where they're up to as
well. Cueing, providing clear and actionable instructions.
Of course, we know why this is important to make sure they're doing the
right form and the right technique.
Regardless of whether we're fixing bad form,
or we're reaffirming good form, the cues we use are
our tool to make sure they're doing the right technique,
quite simply. And lastly,
we've got encourage, motivating and supporting our clients.
Of course, you still need to chuck this in there,
boosting their morale, make them feel themself and encourage effort.
All three of these are extremely crucial and they all have a place in
coaching. So, when I'm coaching someone,
I'm alternating or cycling through all three of these,
which we will go through shortly.
So, we'll start with count.
Maintains the rhythm. Make sure they know where they're up to.
Helps them keep consistent and pacing throughout the rest
of their exercise in terms of where they're up to.
It ensures that they're doing the right number of reps because we know they've
done 12, 12, 12. or 10,
10, 10. And of course it helps us track their progress which
is something we'll talk about later but we are always trying to progressively overload
whether it's with weights or whether it's in reps or both.
So some tips is to first of all count out loud to
keep the client engaged. It reaffirms them that they know that they're
full confident that you're keeping track of their rep count.
If you're not counting, they're not counting for sure and it's the least they
expect out of your service. Vocalizing it helps them keep
aware of. of what number they're up to.
It, once again,
it's about that pace and consistency as well.
counting during daily activities guys.
It's really really important. As soon as you finish this module,
you start practicing. Because there's a high likelihood once we do this,
you'll be struggling to count in your head. It's a lot harder than you
think. So count during your daily activities,
you know, such as brushing your teeth.
One, two, three,
similar automatic activities,
etc. But ultimately the only way to- improve your counting skills
is this food practice. It becomes a memory,
muscle memory. It's hard to even explain it.
It's like riding a bike. You just get good at it and it just
becomes natural. So,
how can I get good at it now though? The best thing you can
do is count- During your own workout.
You might be even not aware of how inaccurate your counting actually is.
So use your workout sessions to practice counting.
It's gonna make your workouts better, more accurate,
and it's gonna make you a better coach. So every time you do a
rep, count it in your head. Like I said.
See ya! Count while brushing your teeth is a great one.
Count from 1 to 12. 1 to 12.
1 to 12. Or count during semi-automatic tasks.
Walking. Clean additions. Make cooking something simple.
Because that's what coaching is right. You are counting while you're- Correcting technique
or having conversation. So it's important we flex and strengthen
that muscle. We're gonna be tracking and practicing lots of our counting when we're
doing our sessions. But the more you're practicing your daily routine guys,
it's gonna pay off heaps. Cause the last thing you want is to be
counting- Thank you for incorrectly. Cause if your client picks that up,
no good. So I've gone to the extent to even have
counting phrases ready for you. Cause you might be thinking do I just count
1, 2, 3, 4? No.
There's an answer to it. The first thing is with counting,
chewing or- oging guys, you don't want to repeat one of them every
single rep. So you don't want to say good job rep 1,
great work rep 2, keep it up rep 3.
And with counting you don't want to say 1,
2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8. You can say for 3 to 4 reps,
maximum. Amen. That's why the first phrase is 2,
3, 4, 5. Once again you want to limit that.
A good phrase is half way there,
how some keep track. It indicates that the midpoint of their set.
When you get towards the end of the set,
it. Typically when you pass Rep 7 to 8,
you want to start to counter down. So formal.
Good John. Two more. And then last one.
Those are the counting specific ones. So just to recap guys,
this is what you do. You start from zero,
you count up. Let's say these are in sports.
Okay, one. Great work.
Good job. Two. Four.
Seven. Then they do number eight.
Great work. Four more. Three more.
one. So you count up. Then you- You count down.
And feel free to chuck in a half way there.
Point. So these ones are number specific.
Then we've got counting phrases that aren't actually numerical.
Almost there. Keep pushing through.
Just a few more. Finish- Strong.
All the way. these are lots of phrases that you will have
in your repertoire. And I'll include a link to these phrases.
Just so you can read through them. And practice them.
These may seem simple. And they are.
Deliciously two to three words long. But when we actually- Ouching at the start,
you're gonna be a bit lost for words. And that's where this comes in.
Learning these phrases allows you to just have a continuous flow of
intentful phrases to say.
So that's counting guys. As soon as you can start practicing counting in your
own head. We count up from zero,
and when we get to the Rep 7.8, if it's a 12 Rep set,
we start to count down. We don't count every single Rep.
And we like to throw in a few encouragement worded phrases in there
too.